שבוע טוב. Shavua Tov.
Today's דף Daf is דף נ. Daf Nun. We're in the middle
of a discussion because the משנה Mishnah said that a husband does
not have חזקה Chazakah on his wife's property because he has a
right to be eating the פירות Peirot from his wife's property. גמרא
Gemara says even if he gives up that right, still we can
assume she's not מקפיד Makpid so he doesn't have a חזקה. Chazakah.
But the implication is that he has a ראיה, Rayah, that if
he brings a שטר, Shtar, obviously then we will assume it's his.
Which should go without saying, but the problem is that we have
this משנה Mishnah that says that if somebody bought from the husband
and then from the wife, that it's not good because the wife
can just say I was doing it to make my husband happy.
So maybe the same should be if he produces a שטר Shtar
that she sold it to him. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
no, that's only talking about where she waves the right, her liens
on property that her husband owns that her husband sold. So if
she's waving her liens, then she could say I did it as
make him happy for two reasons. Number one is she's not really
giving up her property, she's just waving certain liens, she still has
that money owed to her. And number two, those liens are to
collect for when he dies or divorces her. So to hold on
to them would create a lot of tension within the marriage. You
know, what? You're waiting for me to die? Okay. So whereas for
to actually sell her property itself, that is something that we would
not say she is doing for the sake of her husband. That's
a significant giving up of her own property and therefore that would
be valid. And if the husband has a שטר, Shtar, has a
document that she sold it to him, that would be valid. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לאתויי נכסי מלוג. Ella l'atuyei
nichsei milog. We'll pick up on דף נ, Daf Nun, five lines
from the top, the word נכסי מלוג. Nichsei Milog. So, but that
idea that the wife is saying I sold it to my I
just did it to make him happy would not include נכסי מלוג,
Nichsei Milog, her own property that she retains title to, that he
just has the right to פירות. Peirot. There, if she signs that
to her husband or to somebody else, it would be valid. So
גמרא Gemara says, one minute, is that really true? הא אמר אממר,
Ha amar Amemar, doesn't אממר Amemar say איש ואשה
שמכרו בנכסי מלוג לא עשו ולא כלום? Ish v'ishah shemachru benichsei milog
lo asu v'lo klum? If they both sold the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei
Milog, it's no good. Which presumably means that the husband and wife
came to a third party and the husband signed over his פירות,
Peirot, and the wife signed over her title. And even though they're
both selling their portion, it sounds like it's no good. So presumably
we're understanding for a similar reason that she's only doing it to
make her husband happy. So you see that applies to נכסי מלוג
Nichsei Milog as well.
They did it together separately?
Well, yeah, you could make that distinction, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. כי איתמר דאממר היכא דזבין איהו ומית אתיא איהי
ומפקא. Ki itmar d'Amemar heicha d'zavin ihu umis atya ihi umafka. So
no, no, rather than together it says the opposite, it says that
when it says איש ואשה, Ish v'ishah, we don't mean 'and' we
mean 'or'. When only one of them sell it, they didn't do
anything. Okay, fine, but even if that's true, if the wife doesn't
do anything when she sells her title, so then that shows that
the wife is never, it's not, it's not serious when she's trying
to sell her title. So now we're going to modify, not only
does it mean the wife or the husband, but when it says
לא עשו ולא כלום, lo asu v'lo klum, that's a bit of
an overstatement. It doesn't mean לא עשו ולא כלום. lo asu v'lo
klum. What it means is it is that it doesn't work for
sort of the, for what they don't have control over. Meaning what?
Meaning, let's say the husband sells his right to the פירות. Peirot.
So the buyer actually gets the right to the פירות. Peirot. So
it's not true, it's not לא עשו ולא כלום. lo asu v'lo
klum. The buyer gets the right to the פירות. Peirot. Okay, but
then let's assume that the husband dies. Okay, or the husband divorces
his wife. That wife's right to the פירות Peirot reverts to the
woman because the husband can't sell more than he owns. So the
same way he's only entitled for it while they're married, he can
only sell the right as long as the two remain married. Okay,
so that's a לא עשו ולא כלום lo asu v'lo klum in
a sort of a permanent sense. But what about the אשה? Ishah?
I'm getting there. Okay, now if a woman sells her קנין הג,
kinyan hag, her ownership of the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milog, okay? So
what does that mean לא עשו ולא כלום? lo asu v'lo klum?
So what it means is, well let's see. She owns title, so
if the husband dies or divorces the wife, this third party now
gets the כל קרקע. Kol karka. Let's say the wife dies first.
So if the wife dies first, what would be the הלכה halachah
if she was still holding on to the title of the נכסי
מלוג? Nichsei Milog? What would be the הלכה? halachah?
He'd inherit her.
Okay. So now would you say oh, so this third party have
to give it back to the husband? But that doesn't make sense
because anytime I buy land from anybody and they die, I should
have to return it to their kids, right? Because that's just an
issue of inheritance. That's not a limit, meaning the fact that the
husband ownership of the פירות Peirot is only during his marriage to
the wife, that's a limit of the degree to which he owns
it. So that's the only amount he can sell. But the wife
owns title free and clear, right? It's totally hers forever. So what
does it mean לא עשו ולא כלום? lo asu v'lo klum? So
the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to that. That's a special
תקנה takanah actually that the husband gets it back even though logically
he shouldn't because the wife totally owned it. So let's take a
look. Okay. היכא דזבין איהו ומית, Heicha d'zavin ihu umis, so if
he sold and then he died, אתיא איהי ומפקא, atya ihi umafka,
she can come and take back the פירות peirot because He only
had the פירות peirot during his life. That makes sense. אי נמי,
Ei nami, now here's the one that doesn't seem to make sense,
זבנה איהי ומתה, zavna ihi umesa, she sold her title and she
died. אתא איהו ומפיק. Asa ihu umafik. Now he can come and
take the title back. Now why is that? It was her property,
she died, tough luck that he doesn't get to inherit her, I
mean, she sold her property. Okay, no, בתקנתא דרבנן. betakanta de-rabbanan. That's
because of a special תקנתא דרבנן. takanta de-rabbanan. וכדרבי יוסי בר חנינא,
Ukhederbi Yose bar Chanina, like the statement of רבי יוסי בר חנינא.
Rebbi Yose bar Chanina. דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, De-amar Rebbi Yose
bar Chanina,
באושא התקינו, be-Usha iskinu, in אושא, Usha, which is one of the
places the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went after they left the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, they made a special תקנה, takana, האשה שמכרה בנכסי מלוג, ha-ishah
she-machra benichsei milog, a woman who sells her נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog,
her property that she has title to that the husband was eating
the פירות, peirot, so ומתה, umesa, then she dies, הבעל מוציא מיד
הלקוחות. habaal motzi miyad halokachot. The husband can retrieve it from the
purchasers, even though again that really should make no sense, but because,
right, because it's, you know, somebody sells something, they die, the kids
don't get to retrieve the land that the person sold, but nevertheless
this is a special תקנה takana that what the גמרא Gemara said
is it made the בעל baal like a לוקח ראשון, lokeach risha,
meaning he wasn't just an inheritor of his wife's property, but if
the wife brings property into the marriage, even if she retains title,
since it's now part of the marriage, it's like he's, basically he's
got first dibs on it, okay, so it's like he since and
he would anticipate inheriting her when she died, so therefore when she
does die, even if she sold it, he can step in and
say no, no, no, it's like I always owned it first, that's
לוקח ראשון, lokeach risha, okay, so it's a special תקנה. takana.
And what was the purpose of that again?
What was the purpose? I don't know, these are we want people
to marry, you know, we want
honeymoon, exactly, you know. I mean it's always an interesting question, right,
like how to play in that dynamics of who's deciding who to
marry whom. Okay, okay, so
therefore that's a הלכה halacha that does not mean that the wife
cannot sell her title, she can sell her title to somebody else,
except with the exception that if she died, the husband retrieves it,
okay, and that's a special תקנה, takana, and she can certainly sell
her title to her husband. אבל היכא דזבינו תרוייהו לעלמא, Aval heicha
d'zivinu tarvaihu le-alma, now
let's say they jointly, what we initially thought it meant, agree to
divest themselves of it. So if they're jointly decide to giving up
their rights to it, then if she died, he wouldn't be able
to retrieve it. Okay, אי נמי זבנה איהי לדידיה, Ei nami zavna
ihi ledidei, or if she sold to him, זינא זביני, zina zivinei,
it's a good sale. So yes, the wife can sell her title
to it and if the husband has a שטר shtar that she
sold, that she sold her title to her husband, you know, then
it actually would be a good שטר. shtar. Okay, so that's one
way of bracketing this statement. We the statement of אמימר Amemar of
אשה שמכרה בנכסי מלוג לא עשתה ולא
כלום, isha she-machra be-nichsei milog lo asva velo klum, it doesn't really
mean לא עשתה ולא כלום, lo asva velo klum, okay, it really
means that it's not a permanent sale if only one of them
did it, but actually if they did it together it works, and
if they did it to one another it works.
Can't you say that if they did it together then he certainly
feels like she has to go along with him?
Yeah, we're not saying that, we're trying, I hear that, but we're
trying to limit that only to the cases of שעבודים, shibudim, not
cases of real ownership. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'is eima, and if you want,
אמימר Amemar who says that לא עשתה ולא כלום, lo asva velo
klum, דאמר כרבי אליעזר, de-amar ke-Rebbi Eliezer, he's going like רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer and his לא עשתה ולא כלום lo asva velo klum
is again having nothing to do with I'm doing it to make
my wife happy, it's עשתה ולא כלום asva velo klum because of
a general position of what happens when neither person is the full
owner. Now and that if neither person is the full owner, they
cannot operate independently of one another. Now this is not like a
שותפות, shutafut, שותפות shutafut is I am I'm a full owner of
fifty percent, okay, but let's say we own different parts of something
in the sense, not physical parts, but in the sense like the
wife and the husband, Bobby here owns the fruit, the rights to
the fruit, I own the title, so neither of our ownership is
really which one would be which would you say would be considered
to be the real owner? On the one hand I have the
title, but on the other hand I can't benefit from it, so
that's not real ownership, ownership is you have to benefit, Bobby gets
the benefit but she doesn't have the title, so this is the
classic question of קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי kinyan peiros ke-kinyan haguf
dami or not, if a person has rights to the פירות, peirot,
are they considered to be the real owner, or is the person
with the title considered to be the real owner? Now if you
think of it that there are four possibilities there, what are the
four possibilities?
Each of you owns fifty...
no, no, no, no, who's the real owner? Don't, not fifty percent,
no, don't own fifty percent, there's a question of the title, who
do we give the title to as you are the real owner,
okay, so there's four possibilities, the one with the פירות peirot is
the real owner, the one with the title, the title is the
real owner, what are the other two possibilities? Both of them are,
neither of them are. Very good. So let's take a look. So
we're going to see what? So we're going to see that the
גמרא's Gemara claim that אמימר Amemar that neither of them can sell
it, the גמרא Gemara says is going like רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
because רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is saying when you split it that
way, neither of them get the title of owner, so therefore neither
of them can, presumably functioning together they can sell it. Okay, but
functioning independently, since neither one is considered owner, you're not even in
a position to transfer your own rights because you do not have
enough of that title of being the owner. Okay, so let's—which is
very strange. Like, fine, let me just transfer my rights. I don't
need the title. But no, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying according
to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, you're not really in a position to
do anything.
So what's the difference between that and a partnership?
Partnership is you own 50 percent but your ownership is an ownership
of title and an ownership of פירות peiros *peiros*. It's just not
on the whole object, okay?
And you own 50 percent of—there is 50 percent that's yours.
But not that we can split it, but you have title to
the tree and you have right to the fruits of the tree,
it's just that it's a share in the tree, it's not 100
percent of it, okay? Can I sell it? Right, yeah, you can
sell your share. Yeah, okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay,
so this—we're going to connect this to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* and to a much broader debate of who is considered to
be the owner. Now, what is the relevance of saying who do
we assign that title to? So there's a lot of הלכות halachos
*halachos*, for example, that the question of who's the owner applies. Like,
for example, let's say I steal an object that somebody has קנין
פירות kinyan peiros, *kinyan peiros* and the other person has קנין הגוף
*kinyan haguf*. I'm a גנב ganav. *gannav*. Who do I pay כפל
kefel *kefel* to? Right, who can—who can sanctify the object, who can
be מקדיש *makdish* the object? Right? There's a lot of הלכות *halachos*
that we want to know, who do we assign the title owner
to? Alright, so let's take a look. The גמרא'ס *Gemara's* going to—is
this a husband and wife issue or it can be
split by—no, by other—by two people, if you—any split that exists like
this, with the—that would be the question, and the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* actually
going to deal with a case that's not husband-wife. Okay, so דתניא
*detanya*, we learned a ברייתא *braisa*: המוכר עבדו ופסק עמו שישמשנו שלשים
יום *Hamocher avdo upasak imo sheyishameshunu sheloshim yom*. Somebody, ראובן
*Reuven*, sold to שמעון *Shimon* his slave, but ראובן *Reuven* said, but
I'm going to hold onto the slave for 30 days. Now, he
didn't just say the sale will only be final in 30 days.
You own the title right now, but I am retaining for myself
the right to use him for the next month, okay? Got to
wrap up some business here, so I'm going to retain the קנין
פירות peiros, *kinyan peiros* in the slave for the next month. Now,
already, by the way, you know, you could say this is—it might
be a little bit different. If I start with owning of the
title and I give you the קנין פירות peiros, *kinyan peiros*, maybe
your קנין פירות peiros. *kinyan peiros* is weaker than if I start
with owning the title and I keep the קנין פירות peiros, *kinyan
peiros*, right? So you, right, then I started as the full owner
and I'm keeping the קנין פירות peiros, *kinyan peiros*, that might make—that
I might have more of that title of owner because I started
as a full owner as opposed to, you know, if somebody gets
the קנין פירות *kinyan peiros*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not
making that distinction. Okay? So המוכר עבדו ופסק עמו שישמשנו שלשים יום
*Hamocher avdo upasak imo sheyishameshunu sheloshim yom*. ראובן *Reuven* sold to שמעון
*Shimon* the slave and ראובן *Reuven* kept the קנין פירות *kinyan peiros*
for 30 days. רבי מאיר אומר *Rabbi Meir omer*: הראשון ישנו בדין
יום או יומיים yom o yomayim *harishon yeshno bedin yom o yomayim*.
The original owner has the הלכה halacha? *halacha* of יום או יומיים
yom o yomayim *yom o yomayim*, one or two days. What's the
הלכה halacha *halacha* of יום או יומיים yom o yomayim *yom o
yomayim*, one or two days? So the תורה *Torah* says that if
a master smites his slave and the slave dies, okay, so this
is actually a radical—like radical, radical, like חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of the
תורה *Torah*, you know, that slaves are not just properties, they're actually
human beings. I mean, it's always very difficult to talk about, you
know, slaves in הלכה halacha *halacha* because yes, that was an institution
in the entire world for, you know, until like what, 150 years
ago or so, okay? So fine, so the תורה *Torah*, you know,
so the תורה *Torah* could not sort of uproot that 3,000 years
before it was time. Alright, but—but at the same time, the תורה
*Torah* says even at the same time that slaves are treated as
property, they're humans and if a master beats his slave and the
slave dies, if a master beats his slave
and takes out an eye or so, the slave goes free. And
if a master beats his slave and the slave dies, the master's
put to death. Like that would be like unheard of, right? Completely
unheard of, that the—that that degree of recognizing the humanity of—the human
beingness, you know, that he's a human, of the slave. So, the
humanist, I guess. So—so that—but the גמרא'ס *Gemara's*—the תורה *Torah* balances that
with, you know, a certain realistic, you know, a reality that there
was the institution of slavery and people
did—they did beat them. So it says, if he dies within a
day or two, then it was clearly a, you know, a cruel,
merciless beating and then the master's put to death. If the slave
lingered for more than a day or two, right, then the master
would not be put to death because the end of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is לא יוקם כי כספו הוא lo yukam ki kaspo
hu. *lo yukam ki chaspo hu*. He will not be avenged because
the slave is the master's property. So it's a fascinating balance between
property and, you know, being a life and being a human being.
Alright, but that only applies to the master. If some stranger beats
the slave, you know, and the slave dies even after many days,
the stranger's put to death. Okay, so it is—so that is the
מצוה *mitzvah* in the תורה *Torah*. By the way, the idea of
יום או יומיים *yom o yomayim*, a day or two, is understood
to mean like a full day, 24 hours. Alright, so who has
the status of master? The one who owns the קנין פירות *kinyan
peiros* or the one who owns the קנין הגוף *kinyan haguf*? And
the relevance would be, only the one who has the status of
master, right, gets—is doesn't get punished if he dies— after one or
two days, whereas somebody else would get put to death even after
one or two days. Okay, yes, Bobby.
I was curious to know if somebody came along and actually murdered
a slave. Yes. But it wasn't his slave.
Put to death.
I understand that. Yes. But does the owner of the slave also
have an entitlement to that as property?
To get compensation? Yes, I assume so. That's a good question. Probably
no because of קמליה. kimlei Yeah, the principle of קמליה that if
somebody does a capital crime that overrides any other civil liabilities. Okay,
but if somebody's ox for somebody else's slave then there is and
the slave dies then there is compensation. Yeah.
So he has this dual status. Okay, so it says so who
has this הלכה? halacha, So רבי מאיר אומר ראשון יש בו דין
יום או יומיים Rabbi Meir omer rishon yesh bo din yom o
yomayim the original master who still has the קניין פירות kinyan peirot
meaning קניין פירות כקניין הגוף. kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf. It's the original
owner that's considered to be the owner. מפני שהוא תחתיו mipnei shehu
tachtav because he is under you know because he is under his
control. Okay, because the פסוק pasuk says ומת תחת ידו umet tachat
yado
if the slave dies under his hand. So the definition of master
at least here the גמרא Gemara. is going to globalize it you
could say maybe they're just debating this מצווה. mitzvah. Okay, but here
but he says no תחת ידו tachat yado the one who actually
is controlling the slave that's the one who's considered the master. Okay,
קסבר קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי. kasavar kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami.
So the גמרא Gemara rather than making it about a local question
of within the הלכה halacha: of a slave and beating a slave
who's considered the master, it makes it a global question. Owning the
rights to the fruit to the produce that makes you considered to
be the master. Like as if you have title. רבי יהודה אומר
השני יש בו דין יום או יומיים. Rabbi Yehuda omer hasheni yesh
bo din yom o yomayim. No, it's the second one the guy
who bought the קניין הגוף kinyan haguf even though he doesn't yet
have the קניין פירות. kinyan peirot. מפני שהוא כספו mipnei shehu kaspo
because the end of the פסוק is לא יוקם כי כספו הוא.
lo yukam ki chaspo hu, A
more than a day or two he will not be avenged because
it is his property. So the second one is the one who's
actual property it is. הראשון אין בו דין יום או יומיים harishon
ein bo din yom o yomayim שאינו כספו. she-eino kaspo. But the
first one not because even though he's still serving the first one
he's not owned by the first one and the exemption is not
the one who right now has a right to use him, the
exemption is for the one who actually owns him. קסבר קניין פירות
לאו כקניין הגוף דמי kasavar kinyan peirot lav kekinyan haguf dami that
owning the fruit is not like you're own you own the actual
title and it's the one who has the title even without the
fruit that is considered to be the master. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi
Yose omer שניהם יש בם דין יום או יומיים. shneihem yesh bam
din yom o yomayim.
They both have the title of master rather the first one the
exemption applies to both of them because זה מפני שהוא תחתיו zeh
mipnei shehu tachtav one because he's under his control ומת תחת ידו
umet tachat yado וזה מפני שהוא כספו ve-zeh mipnei shehu kaspo
and the other because he actually is purchased and owned by him
entitled. ומסתפקא ליה umistaflei
now you could say how could actually is it possible that you
could actually have two masters like I don't know you know what
would happen if somebody stole the slave or whatever forgetting that there's
no גניבה gneiva but somebody stole an object by whatever by like
you know with a גנב. Would you pay כפל kefel to both?
Maybe you pay כפל to them and they split it or something.
Now why not? Maybe the same way by שותפין shutfin you can
have two titles two masters maybe here too. So the גמרא Gemara
actually could have stopped there right? If you have two שותפין shutfin
who own a slave not a division of קניין פירות kinyan peirot
does each one own fifty percent which is a classic case in
the גמרא. Gemara Presumably either one would be exempt of would have
the principle of יום או יומיים would have this exemption. So the
גמרא Gemara could have just stopped here. They both are equally entitled
to that title. Okay but it actually says no actually rather than
saying they both definitely have the title it says he doesn't know
which one to assign the title to. Okay ומסתפקא ליה umistaflei he's
uncertain אי קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי אי לאו כקניין הגוף דמי.
ee kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami ee lav kekinyan haguf dami. We
don't know which one to assign you know whether we treat the
right of fruit as it makes you the owner or not how
we don't know how to פסקן pasken about that and therefore וספק
נפשות להקל vesafek nefashot lehakeil
and therefore we are not going to execute either person because you
know the the status and the exemption of יום או יומיים might
apply to either master so therefore they both get off. Again not
exactly clear why it had to say that why it couldn't say
that you have two masters the same way if you have שותפין
shutfin you have two masters. Okay anyway that's possibility number three and
now we get to possibility number four. Neither of them are the
master. רבי אליעזר אומר שניהם אינם בדין יום או יומיים Rabbi Eliezer
omer shneihem einam bdin yom o yomayim because you need both qualities
כספו kaspo and תחתיו tachtav and without both qualities you're not the
master and you don't get the exemption. Okay so זה לפי שאינו
תחתיו וזה לפי שאינו כספו. zeh lefi she-eino tachtav ve-zeh lefi she-eino
kaspo.
And therefore so that was a fascinating debate by a slave we're
assuming that that is not just a local debate of the הלכה
halacha. of יום או יומיים it's a global debate of who's considered
to be the master now the problem is is that there are
other גמרות Gemaras that don't work exactly with this that have similar
debates of exactly this type of a question but okay we're going
to bracket that. All right and therefore we're going to say according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, that neither is the master but that
would actually mean is is that you are not in a position
to even sell your portion. So therefore the wife can't sell her
קניין הגוף Kinyan HaGuf and the husband can't sell his קניין הפירות.
Kinyan HaPeiros. Probably if they're working in concert they can, because then
they're like as a team divesting themselves of it. And similarly, the
wife would be able to sell her title to her husband, which
gets back to our earlier question: if a husband has a שטר
shtar but the wife sold the title to her נכסי מלוג, nichsei
milog, it's valid, because, you know, then you're allowing one person, essentially,
you're not operating against the other person's, you know, title, you're actually
investing the person fully with that title. So that presumably would work;
to give the other person the ownership would work. But to exercise
your rights to give it to a third party when there's a
different person here that also has a claim, you know, either קניין
פירות kinyan peiros or קניין הגוף, kinyan ha-guf, you're not enough in
a position of authority to do that. Yes.
So in רבי אליעזר, who owns
the slave?
Well,
they both have different set—different ownership of the slave, but neither of
them has... What? The קניין הגוף kinyan ha-guf has the title to
it. קניין הפירות Kinyan ha-peiros has the right to use—use it. So
they both own what they own, but neither of them has the
title of, like, the master.
It's a very interesting situation.
No mas—he's not manumitted. Right.
But he
doesn't have a master.
Right. I mean, they can—they have the right to use him, employ
him, but in הלכות that require like identifying who is the ow—who
is the master. It's a very strange idea.
Legal language looks for clarity.
I know, it's definitely very strange. Let's just—let's just finish the last
line. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi
Eliezer, what's the reason Rabbi Eliezer? אמר קרא, Amar kra, לא יוקם
כי כספו הוא, he will not be avenged because he is his
property. כספו המיוחד לו, Chaspo ha-meyuchad lo, only if it's your property
solely yours. Now again, that does not mean to exclude שותפות, shutfus,
but solely yours in the sense of, like, you have full exercise
of that ownership. You both have the title and the right to
benefit from—you have the קניין הגוף kinyan ha-guf and the קניין הפירות.
kinyan ha-peiros. And without that, we can't really consider you to be
a full master. Okay, a full owner. So again, it's interesting to
imagine, as Rabbi Dov was asking, what are the other implications of
this? Yes.
Could you say that according to all opinions, if within this, you
know, this partnership or whatever you want to call it... Yes. ...can
sell the rights of what they have to the other.
Presumably, because then you're not operating against, right?
That according to every—every opinion.
Yes, yes, that would certainly seem to be true. Okay, so that
is the end of the discussion of a husband having חזקה chazakah
in his wife's property. Of course he doesn't, because he has rights
to the fruit. But as again the גמרא Gemara said, even if
the husband gave up those rights, he still doesn't have a חזקה
chazakah because we assume that the wife is okay with him using
it, won't be מוחל, mocheil, will be מוחל mocheil if he—if he
benefits from the fruit. But if he has evidence that she sold
it to him, it's good. And we don't say she did it
under pressure, and we don't say that, you know, here, that she
wasn't in a position—she's not able to sell her property; that actually
does work. Okay, ולאיש חזקה בנכסי אשתו. V'lo l'ish chazakah b'nichsei ishto.
Now the
reverse—I'm sorry, not the reverse, we're still on the same one. Okay.
Now, a man does not have a חזקה chazakah in his wife's
property. So, I don't know why we requoted the משנה Mishna because
we're still on the same topic, but we're going to look at
it from a different perspective. Okay. דאמר רב, D'amar Rav, אשת איש
צריכה למחות. eshet ish tzricha limchos. One minute, but Rav said that
a married woman has to be מוחל mocheil when somebody's on her
property, has to protest. Okay, now, who does she have to protest
against? Either a third party or her husband. So her husband wouldn't
seem to make sense because the משנה Mishna says that her husband
just automatically doesn't have a חזקה. chazakah.
Well, that—that may be true, but everyone else may not know that.
So why does she have to be מוחל? mocheil?
No, I mean, like, you know, look at this...
Okay, so let's take a look. דמאן? D'man? אילימא באחר, Ileyma b'acher,
if it's a third party, that she doesn't have to protest. Now,
why would she not have to protest about a third—I mean, excuse
me, why would she have to protest? By a third party? Because
what do you mean why she have to protest? A third party
is on her property; she has to protest, you know, or else
the guy's going to get a חזקה. chazakah. So the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, ואמר רב, v'amar Rav, but Rav himself said, אין
מחזיקין בנכסי אשת איש, ein machzikin b'nichsei eshet ish, that you cannot—a
third party cannot have a חזקה chazakah against a married woman's property.
Why do you think that is? Okay, my wife here, she's got
property, I have the קניין הפירות. kinyan ha-peiros. Michael is on the
land. What? What
happened?
The husband loses his rights to the...
Okay, but so, you know we're like protecting the
husband, but if she could actually sell—well, I guess that gets back
to the principal discussion before, whether she could sell it or not.
But assuming that she could, like, sell it, right, so why can't
somebody, like, get a חזקה chazakah on it? So it's actually interesting
here: who's supposed to be מוחל? mocheil? Well, she's the owner, so
if somebody else is... The guy who's eating right now, Michael here
who's eating that property, right, who's—who's, like, whose rights is he compromising,
right? Who's he doing an offense against? Immediately he's doing an offense
against me. Right because he's taking the פירות that should be mine.
Okay, so maybe like I should be מוחה. mocheh. Okay, but on
the other hand it's not my property. His eating of it, right,
is demonstrating that he's the owner, right? So that really is for
my wife to be מוחה. mocheh. Okay, but it's, but it's not
sort of impacting her right away, although nevertheless she should be concerned
that your eating of it will demonstrate that you're the owner. So
why אין מחזיקין? ein machazikin? So let's take a look here at
the רשב"ם Rashbam what he says about this. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says אין מחזיקין. ein machazikin. It's about ten lines before the lines
get wide, beginning of a line: אין מחזיקין מנכסי אשת איש, ein
machazikin minechasei eshes ish, says the רשב"ם, Rashbam, דמצי אמרה אבעלי סמכתי,
dematzi amrah aba'ali samachti, שהוא ימחה ויערער. shehu yimcheh veye'areir. No, you
know, my husband, he's the guy in the field, you know, he's
the man of the family, he's the, he does deals with these
things anyway. I don't know, my house my wife deals with all
of that. Anyway, but okay, so I assumed he was going to
deal with it, you know, it's taking away his fruit, so ובשביל
זה שתקתי. uvishvil zeh shatakti. He didn't say anything. Okay. ובשאר בני
אדם דלאו בעל קא מרע.
uvishar benei adam
delav ba'al ka marei.
Okay, אין מחזיקין. ein machazikin. Now, so, okay, now presumably though the
husband, he could protest, but his silence is not what's relevant. What's
relevant is the silence of the owner. The only person whose silence
is going to show that somebody else owns the property is the
silence of the owner. So although the husband should have protested, right,
oh, the fact you didn't protest shows your wife must have sold,
we can't take your silence as evidence that, you know, to hurt
against your wife. Okay, maybe you could as like, you know, in
secular court because it's circumstantial evidence. But in הלכה, it's the silence
of the owner which is an admission, an implicit admission that the
other person owned it. So the husband is the one who should
have said something, but even so his silence is not a, evidence
that the original owner owns it and the original owner's silence could
say it doesn't mean anything because I assumed my husband would do
it. Now, it raises interesting questions about let's say we had another
example like that. Let's say, I don't know, let's say Michael here
was, there was a משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta desura, you know, Michael's on
my property benefiting from it for five years because of paying off
of a
loan and Eli went ahead and was, and was squatting and was
and was taking all of the produce. So Michael should have protested
because he's taking away, you know, the produce that should be Michael's.
But it's, but, you know, but I'm the owner. So maybe he
doesn't have a חזקה. chazakah. It's interesting to think about how that
works. The one who protests is not the owner and it's the
owner who should be protesting and the one, it's the owner's silence
that is relevant. But it sounds like in a normal case we
would say no, even though Michael is the one that's being hurt
immediately, if Eli is there acting as the owner and taking the
produce, I should be protesting to protect my investment, to protect my
property. But by the wife she can always say I let my
husband handle the business dealing. Okay, and therefore the חזקה chazakah does
not work. So therefore רב Rav says a third party has a
very new fascinating הלכה: a third party does not have a חזקה
chazakah on the נכסי מלוג nichsei melog of the wife because she
can always say I was not protesting because I was relying on
my husband. So if that's true, if that's true then when רב
Rav says that an אשת איש צריכה למחות, eshes ish tzerichah limchos,
that she has to protest, which means you can have a חזקה
chazakah on it, it must be when her husband takes possession. But
that goes against our משנה Mishnah because our משנה Mishnah says a
husband doesn't have חזקה chazakah on his wife's property. Okay, אלא לאו
בבעל, ela lav beva'al, it must be when the husband takes possession.
So I don't understand, the husband shouldn't have a חזקה, chazakah, that's
our משנה. Mishnah. רב Rav says a third party doesn't have חזקה,
chazakah, right, because she relies on her husband. So what's the case
where somebody has a חזקה, chazakah, where רב Rav says she has
to be מוחה? mocheh? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so how do you assign that one case where somebody could
have a חזקה? chazakah? לעולם בבעל. le'olam beva'al. Okay, it is the
husband. כגון שחפר בה בורות שיחין ומערות, kegon shechafar bah boros shichin
ume'aros,
and it's a case where the husband dug like cisterns and wells
and, you know, ditches and those types of things. So he's actually
making changes, physical changes to the property itself. He's not just getting
the פירות, he's actually dam- potentially damaging the property. All right. Maybe
improving it. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says we have to be assuming
that it's a type of property that normally would not call for
these things, okay. So I don't know, he's got this brilliant idea:
I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to build a hotel
here on this wheat field and, you know, if you build it
they will come, right? So he's building a hotel in the middle
of nowhere. So he thinks he's improving it, but a normal owner
feels that's not the right type of thing to be doing in
this field.
So that's not taking פירות, that's
right, that's making, right, a principal, you know, a change to the
actual property, to the principal itself, to the property itself. So there,
that's a case where where if the husband does it and she's
silent, then he would have a חזקה. chazakah. Presumably though, interestingly, if
a third party would do it, it wouldn't be a חזקה chazakah
because she could just say I'm wa- I'm assuming. My husband will
be מוחה moche for me, you know, I'm giving, you know, he
has קנין פירות, I let him deal with those things. Okay, so
a third party now does not have any חזקה, chazakah, it sounds
like, we'd, we had never heard that before, even if you make
principal changes, okay, but structural changes, but the husband can have a
חזקה chazakah when he does more than just take the פירות.
Could you remind us briefly what the משכנתא דסורא mashkanta d'sura is?
Yeah, I just threw that in before. I don't, that's when, when
somebody, I borrow money and you're on my property now and for
a certain period of time and you're taking something from the fruit
or whatever, and that's paying off my debt.
That's
right.
Yeah, so there's the
money and the, the balance between
husband and
wife, is that ever,
when did that go, the marriage and in terms of property? Well,
what is? That he can actually do that? He's like undermining the
idea that it's actually really her property.
No, they're not. They're protecting the idea that it's her property. If
he does those types of changes, he was not allowed to do
that. Right. That's right. Yes. He's in violation. But he has a
חזקה chazakah because he's not allowed to. Because he's not allowed to,
her, it's an adverse act and her silence becomes a confession. Okay.
Having a חזקה chazakah is only based on the fact that he
wasn't allowed to do it. All right. All right. And the חזקה
chazakah would then be evidence, if she's quiet in the face of
him doing that, it must be she sold it to him. Yes.
So no one could ever have a חזקה chazakah on a married
woman's property.
A third party. A third party. According to this, that is correct.
So weird. So why wouldn't we say then it was the husband's
responsibility to make a,
we did, so that's what I was saying before. It might have
been the husband's responsibility, but his silence is not a confession. You
only, only the silence of the owner can be proof that the
person sold it. How can you use somebody, it's a very convenient
position, it help protects, I know it protects the wife's interest. So
if you buy property from a married woman, you had better hold
on to your שטר. shtar. Yeah. Okay.
How can you say this is evidence that she sold it to
him, maybe she gave it to him? Doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter. Giving or selling, who cares, either way he owns
it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והאמר רב נחמן v'ha'amar
Rav Nachman now,
the question is also, is that a חזקה chazakah immediately? It could
be that when you do something like actual damage, maybe you don't
even need three years, right? Maybe the immediate silence in the face
of actual doing destructive acts to the property could be seen of
as immediate חזקה. chazakah. All right, so I think the, so let's
take a look,
one minute, let's see if the רשב״ם Rashbam says it. And
somebody says it over the משיני. mishini.
Okay. Okay, so anyway, so somebody said here, maybe it's גמרא gemara
coming up. Okay, so now see what the גמרא says, ואמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אין חזקה לנזיקין. v'amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha ein chazakah l'nezikin. One minute, when you do damaging
acts, that's not חזקה. chazakah. חזקה chazakah is when you eat the
פירות, when you do destructive acts it's not חזקה, chazakah, which is
strange.
What destructive act? A בורות?
boros? Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Okay. Well, it's destructive in a context where
that would not be what the field would call for. Okay. I
understand. אימא, eima, no, אין דין חזקה לנזיקין. ein din chazakah l'nezikin.
No, no. אין חזקה לנזיקין ein chazakah l'nezikin means the opposite. It
means we don't go by the normal requirements of three years. Because
it is something that is actually destroying the property or damaging, right,
then you actually get a חזקה chazakah immediately. Okay, if you, right,
I think take a look at the רשב״ם, Rashbam, he says, I'll
just read you one line,
אין דין חזקה, ein din chazakah, about ten lines down in the
wide lines, in the middle lines, להצריך ג' שנים לנזיקין היכא דחזקתו
על ידי נזיקין אלא לאלתר הוי חזקה שאין אדם רואה שמזיקין קרקע
שלו ושותק אלא מוחה מיד. l'hatzrich gimmel shanim l'nezikin heicha d'chazkato al
yedei nezikin ela l'altar hvei chazakah she'ein adam roeh shemazikin karka shelo
v'shotek ela moche miyad. Okay, it completely reverses the meaning of the
line, but okay. So one scenario is the husband is doing now,
again, it's true, it's not really destruction, he's doing what in his
mind is an improvement, but it's a, but if it's not the
normal type of thing that would be done here, it's put in
the category of damage, because damage is a change to the principal
property, you know, to the actual, to the actual principal, that's not
warranted. Yes.
So let's say he wants to put a building on the field.
Right. Why would you not think that she thinks, okay, that may
make my land more valuable, he'll still get the פירות, the, you
know, the rent or whatever?
Yeah, that's a good question. So if he's doing a בורות, boros,
even if for normal people, people don't build בורות boros here in
the middle of the field, but since it's not an actual destructive
act, maybe he convinced her that it was a good idea, right?
So that's a good question. Like why is that good enough to
be a חזקה chazakah when it's not obviously, like if it's something
that you could assume that she would think this is crazy, my
husband gets these crazy ideas, but how do you know? How is
it a strong enough evidence? Maybe like, right, it's a good question,
right? I don't know. That's a really good question because maybe she,
maybe he convinced her that this would be a good idea.
Yeah,
that's also a good question. How much? Like does he have a
day? Does he have a week? Right? You have to give him
a little bit, you have to give some time to like respond,
right?
Maybe 30 days.
Right. Yeah, I don't know. I know we had לאלתר l'altar before
about this as well, like you know according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe
Yehuda, right, who says that there's a חזקה לאלתר. chazakah l'altar. The
time of three years was only to get the message in. How
long is לאלתר? l'altar? Right, I yeah, I don't know. Okay, so
now, that's one answer, but I you know Gloria's question is a
very good one. As long as it's not you know clearly destructive,
even if it would seem to be like something that normal people
would consider, you know maybe, maybe she's going along with it. So
I don't know the answer to that. איבעית אימא Ibayeima if you
want I could say, לאו אתמר עלה lav itmar lah רב מרי
Rav Mari אמר בקוטורא. amar Be-Kutra. No, no, no.
So not changing our basic answer about when the husband has חזקה
chazakah on his wife's field. We're just reinterpreting this phrase of אין
חזקה לנזיקין. Ein chazakah lenizikin. אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin does
not mean when I damage your field I can't get a חזקה
chazakah in it. What it means is that if I am going
back way back to, it seems so long ago, remember the issues
of the second פרק perek when I'm doing things in my yard
and they're bothering you, right? Remember that, the laws of neighbors? So
let's say I am here, I don't know, barbecuing and the smoke
is going into your yard and it's getting in your eyes, and
you haven't been saying anything. So do I get a חזקה chazakah
in the sense of your silence means that you have waived your
right to complain about this and now if it starts bothering you,
you can't complain anymore? We had some of that discussion earlier. So
אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin means not as a way of
getting claiming ownership to a field. When I am doing something that
is causing you damage and you are being silent about it, does
that mean that you have you know waived your right to complain?
And the answer אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin is no. If
you're being damaged, you always, even if you were silent, can now
protest. Okay, only under certain cases, there's some cases where you actually
can't protest anymore.
And משנה ז Mishna zayin has a flow like that.
Yeah, yeah, that's true, I didn't notice that.
Let's read it. Okay. לאו אתמר עלה lav itmar lah רב מרי
Rav Mari אמר בקוטורא amar Be-Kutra with though like the you know
smoke. רב זביד Rav Zvid אמר בבית הכסא, amar Be-veis hakissei, the
smell of an outhouse. So things that are considered to be very
damaging, like very like you know in your face as it were,
you know these types of smells or smoke or whatever, even if
you've been doing it for a while, I can now protest and
get you to stop doing it. Yes, Jenna, you had a question.
Even when we say it's actually אין דין חזקה? Ein din chazakah?
So we know we're giving a new interpretation.
But does that go back and affect those cases?
Yes, so now maybe if you want to get a חזקה chazakah
by doing damage maybe you would need three years.
אין דין חזקה Ein din chazakah means you don't need three years
when I'm damaging your field, it's automatic. Now we say אין חזקה
לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin means you know if you've been making smoke
in my yard, you don't have a you know, and I haven't
protested, you don't get a right to keep on doing it, I
can now protest. So that original אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin
now has nothing to do with the question of possession of somebody
else's yard. Right? So now in that case maybe it would require,
if that's what you're asking, once we give a new interpretation,
do you get immediate חזקה chazakah by doing damaging acts or do
you need three years, now maybe you would say you need three
years. You know, that's not clear of how we would go back
about that.
So on this point part of what's going on right now in
the סוגיא sugia is we have this concept אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein
chazakah lenizikin and we're trying to say what type of facts or
what type of case does that?
Yeah, what does that line mean? Does it mean about a חזקה
chazakah of field? And אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin means the
opposite of what it sounds like and it means you get חזקה
chazakah right away? Or does אין חזקה לנזיקין Ein chazakah lenizikin go
back to the second פרק perek and that if you haven't been
complaining about damaging things that are coming into your yard,
you do not give up
your right to continue to complain about them? Okay.
And then right away reasoning to that where
it says as
soon as I make a barbecue and you don't speak...
Right, no, but it's the opposite, there it says even if you've
been quiet for a long time, you always retain the right to
complain. Okay, so we now say, so just review where we are.
Number one is that we've introduced the idea that a third party
doesn't have חזקה chazakah on a wife's property, which is quite fascinating
because she can just say I was assuming my husband would deal
with it and the husband's silence doesn't mean anything. Can the husband
ever have חזקה chazakah on his wife's property? And we're saying yes,
if he makes principal changes. Okay, now would that be immediate or
only after three years? That might depend on how we read that
line of אין חזקה לנזיקין. Ein chazakah lenizikin. All right, now the
גמרא is going to move on. Okay, let's take a look.
רב
יוסף אמר לעולם באחר. Rav Yosef amar Le'olam beacher. No, no, no.
There would be a case that a third party could have a
חזקה chazakah on his wife's property, even though she could normally say
I'm letting my husband deal with it. Why? Going back. כגון שאכלה
מקצת חזקה בחיי הבעל ושלוש לאחר מיתת הבעל. Kegon she'achlah miktzas chazakah
bechayei habaal veshalosh leachar misas habaal.
Okay. So the case would be that the person ate while the
wife was married, he began eating the fruit of the land. Then
the husband died and he ate it for three years. So now
here's an interesting question. Would that be a חזקה? chazakah? Three years
she was a widowed woman, no husband. She can't say I relied
on my husband. But could she say since you started with it
when my husband was around, I wasn't paying attention even after my
husband died? Or do we say, no, no, no, at that stage
you don't have a claim.
It says דאכלה d'achla in the feminine. I don't get that.
דאכלה, d'achla, the field, the
שדה. sadeh. ואכלה, v'achla, right, exactly. כגון שאכלה מקצת חזקה בחיי הבעל
ושלש אחר מיתת הבעל. kegon she'achla miktzat chazakah b'chayei habaal v'shalosh achar
misat habaal. So in that case, now she can no longer say,
oh, I didn't say anything for three years after my husband was
dead because you started when my husband was alive, I didn't pay
attention. No, no, no. If it's three years after the husband is
dead, you're on your own now. You know, once your husband is
dead, you're like anybody else. Okay? In that case, now it creates
this funny מיגו. migo. מיגו דאי בעי אמר ליה אנא זבינתיה מינך,
migo d'i baei amar leh ana zevintiah minach, he could have said
I bought it from you after your husband died, so כי אמר
לה נמי את זבינתיה ליה וזבנה ניהלי, ki amar lah nami at
zevintiah leh v'zavnah nihali, you first sold it to your husband and
he sold it to me
while your husband was still alive, מהימן, meheman, he'd be believed. But
the real חידוש chiddush is not the מיגו. migo. The real חידוש
chiddush is that now that the husband is dead, you can have
a חזקה chazakah on this land, even if the חזקה chazakah began
while the husband is alive.
She can no longer say I'm relying on him.
Exactly.
And then back to three. Exactly. Okay.
But nobody saw sit on the roof?
Right, exactly. Okay, so now we've got that. We've got that a
third party cannot have חזקה chazakah on the property of a married
woman while she is a married woman, and the husband... so that's
a big חידוש which was not in our משנה. mishnah. And maybe
in some cases the husband can have חזקה chazakah on his wife's
property when he makes principal changes. Okay, גופא. gufa. אמר רב. amar
Rav. Let's go back to the statement we said before. אמר רב
אין מחזיקין בנכסי אשת איש. amar Rav ein machzikin b'nichsei eshet ish.
A third party, like we said before, cannot have חזקה chazakah on
the married woman's property. She can always say I was letting my
husband handle it. ודייני גולה אמרו, u'dayanei golah amru, but the judges
of the exile said, so מחזיקין. machzikin. I don't know who's the...
so the גמרא says, רשב"ם Rashbam says who's דייני גולה? dayanei golah?
שמואל Shmuel וקרנא. v'Karna. So these were two major דיינים. dayanim. Okay.
Yep, קרנא Karna is his name. Okay. אמרו מחזיקין. amru machzikin. You
do have a חזקה. chazakah. Now that's a brand-new הלכה. We don't
hold of that. Let her protest, it's her property. אמר רב הלכה
כדייני גולה. amar Rav halacha k'dayanei golah. We rule like them, that
you can have a חזקה. chazakah. אמרו ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי
לרב, amru leh Rav Kahana v'Rav Assi l'Rav, הדר ביה מר משמעתיה?
hadar beh mar mishemateih? Have you reversed your position? Because you were
the one who was saying that you can't have חזקה chazakah on
a married woman's property, and now you're ruling like them? אמר להו
מסתברא אמי כדרב יוסף. amar lehu mistavra ami k'deRav Yosef. No, no,
no. I really didn't mean that I rule like them, meaning I
would like to believe that when they say you have a חזקה,
chazakah, it's like what רב יוסף Rav Yosef said before, when you're
actually making like, you know, this case about three years after the
husband died. Of course that's not as רשב"ם Rashbam says, that's not
really what they said. They said you really can have a חזקה
chazakah on a married woman's property. Okay, but רב Rav is saying
we'll go like them after the husband died. Okay, but again, they
really argue on רב Rav and they say you can have a
חזקה chazakah on a woman's property, and we end with that debate.
Okay, so we'll end with this for today, and a little early.